<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[OSv Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://osv.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2016-04-21T12:47:13-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://osv.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cloudius Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NFS on OSv or “How I Learned to Stop Worrying About Memory Allocations and Love the Unikernel”]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2016/04/21/nfs-on-osv/"/>
    <updated>2016-04-21T07:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2016/04/21/nfs-on-osv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Benoît Canet and Don Marti</strong></p>

<h2>A new type of OSv workload</h2>

<p>The MIKELANGELO project aims to bring High Performance Computing (HPC) to the cloud. HPC traditionally involves bleeding edge technologies, including lots of CPU cores, <a href="http://www.infinibandta.org/">Infiniband</a> interconnects between nodes, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Message_Passing_Interface">MPI</a> libraries for message passing, and, surprise&mdash;NFS, a very old timer of the UNIX universe.</p>

<p>In an HPC context this networked filesystem is used to get the data inside the compute node before doing the raw computation, and then to extract the data from the compute node.</p>

<h2>Some OSv NFS requirements</h2>

<p>For HPC NFS is a must,  so we worked to make it happen. We had some key requirements:</p>

<ul>
<li>The NFS driver must go reasonably fast</li>
<li>The implementation of the NFS driver must be done very quickly to meet the schedule of the rest of the MIKELANGELO project</li>
<li>There is no FUSE (Filesystem in User Space) implementation in OSv</li>
<li>OSv is a C++ unikernel, so the implementation must make full usage of its power</li>
<li>The implementation must use the OSv VFS (Virtual File System) layer, and so be transparent for the application</li>
</ul>


<h2>Considering alternatives</h2>

<p>The first possibility that we can exclude right away is doing an NFS implementation from scratch. This subproject is simply too short on time.</p>

<p>The second possibility is to leverage an implementation from an existing mainstream kernel and simply port it to OSv. The pro would be code reuse, but this comes with a lot of cons.</p>

<ul>
<li>Some implementation licenses do not match well with the unikernel concept where everything can be considered a derived work of the core kernel</li>
<li>Every operating system has its own flavor of VFS. The NFS subproject would be at risk of writing wrappers around another operating system’s VFS idiosyncrasies</li>
<li>Most mainstream kernel memory allocators are very specific and complex, which would leads to more insane wrappers.</li>
</ul>


<p>The third possibility would be to use some userspace NFS implementation, as their code is usually straightforward POSIX and they provide a nice API designed to be embedded easily in another application. But wait! Didn’t we just say the implementation must be in the VFS, right in the middle of the OSv kernel? There is no FUSE on OSv.</p>

<h2>Enter the Unikernel</h2>

<p>Traditional UNIX-like operating system implementations are split in two:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Kernel space:</strong> a kernel doing the low level plumbing everyone else will use</li>
<li><strong>User space:</strong> a bunch of applications using the facilities provided by the kernel in order to accomplish some tasks for the user</li>
</ul>


<p>One twist of this split is that kernel space and user space memory addresses are totally separated by using the MMU (Memory Management Unit) hardware of the processor. It also usually implies two totally different sets of programing APIs, one for kernel space and one for user space, and needless to say a lot of memory copies each time some data must cross the frontier from kernel space to userspace.</p>

<p>A unikernel such as OSv is different. There is only one big address space and only one set of programing APIs. Therefore you can use POSIX and Linux userspace APIs right in an OSv driver. So no API wrappers to write and no memory copies.</p>

<p>Another straightforward consequence of this is that standard memory management functions including malloc(), posix_memalign(), free() and friends, will just work inside an OSv driver. There are no separate kernel-level functions for managing memory, so no memory allocator wrappers needed.</p>

<h2>Meet libnfs</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/sahlberg/libnfs">libnfs</a>, by Ronnie Sahlberg, is a user space NFS implementation for Linux, designed to be embedded easilly in an application.</p>

<p>It’s already used in successful programs like Fabrice Bellard’s <a href="http://wiki.qemu.org/Main_Page">QEMU</a>, and the author is an established open source developer who will not disappear in a snap.</p>

<p>Last by not last, the libnfs license is LGPL. So far so good.</p>

<h2>The implementation phase</h2>

<p>The implementation phase went fast for a networked filesystem. Reviewing went smoothly thanks to Nadav Har’El’s help, and the final post on the osv-devel mailing list was the following:</p>

<p><a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/osv-dev/ACSim3AFSAQ">OSV nfs client</a></p>

<p>Some extra days were spent to fix the occasional bugs and polish the result and now the MIKELANGELO HPC developers have a working NFS client.</p>

<h2>Some code highlights</h2>

<h3>Almost 1:1 mapping</h3>

<p>Given the unikernel nature of OSv, an useful system call like truncate(), used to adjust the size of a file, boils down to</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='cpp'><span class='line'><span class="k">static</span> <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">nfs_op_truncate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">struct</span> <span class="n">vnode</span> <span class="o">*</span><span class="n">vp</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">off_t</span> <span class="n">length</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">err_no</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">auto</span> <span class="n">nfs</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">get_nfs_context</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">vp</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">err_no</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">err_no</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">err_no</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="kt">int</span> <span class="n">ret</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">nfs_truncate</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">nfs</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">get_node_name</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">vp</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="n">length</span><span class="p">);</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">if</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">ret</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
</span><span class='line'>       <span class="k">return</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">ret</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="p">}</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="n">vp</span><span class="o">-&gt;</span><span class="n">v_size</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">length</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'>
</span><span class='line'>   <span class="k">return</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="p">}</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>OSv allowed us to implement this syscall with a very thin shim without involving any additional memory allocation wrapper.</p>

<h3>C++ empowers you to do powerful things in kernel code</h3>

<p>One of the known limitation of libnfs is that it’s not thread-safe. See this <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!msg/libnfs/3Oct9Zvv7D8/vkN9wBp6V0YJ">mailing list posting on multithreading and preformance</a>.  OSv is threaded&mdash;so heavily threaded that there is no concept of a process in OSv, just threads. Clearly this is a problem, but OSv is written in modern C++, which provides us with modern tools.</p>

<p>This single line allows us to work around the libnfs single threaded limitation.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='cpp'><span class='line'><span class="n">thread_local</span> <span class="n">std</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">unordered_map</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">std</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">string</span><span class="p">,</span>
</span><span class='line'>                               <span class="n">std</span><span class="o">::</span><span class="n">unique_ptr</span><span class="o">&lt;</span><span class="n">mount_context</span><span class="o">&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">_map</span><span class="p">;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Here the code makes an associative map between the mount point (the place in the filesystem hierarchy where the remote filesystem appears) and the libnfs <code>mount_context</code>.</p>

<p>The one twist to notice here is <code>thread_local</code>: this single C++ keyword automatically makes a separate instance of this map per thread. The consequence is that every thread/mount point pair can have its own separate <code>mount_context</code>. Although an individual <code>mount_context</code> is not thread-safe, that is no longer an issue.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>As we have seen here, the OSv unikernel is different in a lot of good ways, and allows you to write kernel code fast.</p>

<ul>
<li>Standard POSIX functions just work in the kernel.</li>
<li>C++, which is not used in other kernels, comes with blessings.</li>
</ul>


<p>Scylla will keep improving OSv with the various MIKELANGELO partners, and we should see exciting new hot technologies like vRDMA on OSv in the not so distant future.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/">MIKELANGELO</a> research project is a three-year research project sponsored by the European Commission&rsquo;s <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/">Horizon 2020</a> program. The goal of MIKELANGELO is to make the cloud more useful for a wider range of applications, and in particular make it easier and faster to run high-performance computing (HPC) and I/O-intensive applications in the cloud. For project updates, visit the <a href="https://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/">MIKELANGELO site</a>, or subscribe to this blog’s <a href="http://www.scylladb.com/feed.xml">RSS feed</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Project Mikelangelo Update]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2016/03/08/project-mikelangelo/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-08T06:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2016/03/08/project-mikelangelo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Nadav Har’El</strong></p>

<p>A year ago, we reported (see <a href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/02/02/mikelangelo/">Researching the Future of the Cloud</a>) that ScyllaDB and eight other industrial and academic partners started the <a href="https://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/">MIKELANGELO</a> research project. MIKELANGELO is a three-year research project sponsored by the European Commission&rsquo;s <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/">Horizon 2020</a> program. The goal of MIKELANGELO is to make the cloud more useful for a wider range of applications, and in particular make it easier and faster to run high-performance computing (HPC) and I/O-intensive applications in the cloud.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.scylladb.com/img/project-mikelangelo-logos.png" alt="company logos" /></p>

<p>Last week, representatives of all MIKELANGELO partners (see company logos above, and group photo below) met with the Horizon 2020 reviewers in Brussels to present the progress of the project during the last year. The reviewers were pleased with the project’s progress, and especially pointed out its technical innovations.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.scylladb.com/img/project-mikelangelo-people.jpeg" alt="project participants group photo" /></p>

<p>Represented by Benoît Canet and yours truly, ScyllaDB presented <a href="http://www.seastar-project.org/">Seastar</a>, our new C++ framework for efficient yet complex server applications. We demonstrated the sort of amazing performance improvements which Seastar can bring, with ScyllaDB &ndash; our implementation of the familiar NoSQL database <a href="http://cassandra.apache.org">Apache Cassandra</a> with the Seastar framework. In the specific use case we demonstrated, an equal mixture of reads and writes, ScyllaDB was 7 times faster (!) than Cassandra. And we didn’t even pick ScyllaDB’s best benchmark to demonstrate  (we’d seen even better speedups in several other use cases). Seastar-based middleware applications such as ScyllaDB hold the promise of making it significantly easier and cheaper to deploy large-scale Web or Mobile applications in the cloud.</p>

<p>Another innovation that ScyllaDB brought to the MIKELANGELO project is <a href="http://osv.io/">OSv</a>, our Linux-compatible kernel specially designed and optimized for running on cloud VMs. Several partners demonstrated running their applications on OSv. One of the cool use cases was aerodynamic simulations done by <a href="http://www.xlab.si/">XLAB</a> and Pipistrel. <a href="http://www.pipistrel.si/">Pipistrel</a> is a designer and manufacturer of innovative and award-winning light aircraft (like the one in the picture below), and running their CFD simulations on the cloud, using OSv VMs and various automation tools developed by XLAB, will significantly simplify their simulation workflow and make it easier for them to experiment with new aircraft designs.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.scylladb.com/img/aircraft.jpeg" alt="Pipistrel aircraft photo" /></p>

<p>Other partners presented their own exciting developments: Huawei implemented RDMA virtualization for KVM, which allows an application spread across multiple VMs on multiple hosts to communicate using RDMA (remote direct-memory-access) hardware in the host. In a network-intensive benchmark, virtualized RDMA improved performance 5-fold. IBM presented improvements to their earlier <a href="http://www.harel.org.il/nadav/homepage/papers/11760-atc13-harel.pdf">ELVIS</a> research, which allow varying the number of cores dedicated to servicing I/O, and achieve incredible amounts of I/O bandwidth in VMs. Ben-Gurion University security researchers implemented a scary “cache side-channel attack” where one VM can steal secret keys from another VM sharing the same host. Obviously their next research step will be stopping such attacks! Intel developed a telemetry framework called “snap” to collect and to analyse all sorts of measurements by all the different cloud components &ndash; VM operating systems, hypervisors, and individual applications. HLRS and GWDG, the super-computer centers of the universities of Stuttgart and Göttingen, respectively, built the clouds on which the other partners’ developments will be run, and brought in use cases of their own.</p>

<p>Like ScyllaDB, all partners in the MIKELANGELO project believe in openness, so all technologies mentioned above have already been released as open-source. We’re looking forward to the next year of the MIKELANGELO project, when all these exciting technologies will continue to improve separately, as well as be integrated together to form the better, faster, and more secure cloud of the future.</p>

<p><strong>For more updates, follow the <a href="http://www.scylladb.com/blog/">ScyllaDB blog</a>.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Building OSv Images Using Docker]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/04/27/docker/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/04/27/docker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By David Jorm and Don Marti</strong></p>

<h2>Why build OSv images under Docker?</h2>

<p>Building OSv from source has several advantages, including the ability to build images targeting different execution environments. The <a href="https://cloudrouter.org">CloudRouter project</a> is working on integrating the build script into its continuous integration system, automatically producing nightly rebuilds of all supported OSv application images.</p>

<p>The main problem with this approach is that it requires a system to be appropriately configured with all the necessary dependencies and source code to run builds. To build a scalable and reproducible continuous integration system, we really want to automate the provisioning of new build servers. An ideal way to achieve this goal is by creating a Docker image that includes all the necessary components to produce OSv image builds.</p>

<h2>osv-builder: a Docker based build/development environment for OSv</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/cloudrouter/osv-builder/">osv-builder Docker image</a> provides a complete build and development environment for OSv, including OSv application images and appliances. It has been developed by <a href="https://github.com/abn/">Arun Babu Neelicattu</a> from <a href="http://iix.net">IIX</a>. To download the image, run:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>docker pull cloudrouter/osv-builder
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>OSv includes a range of <a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/osv/tree/master/scripts">helper scripts</a> for building and running OSv images. The build script will compile OSv from the local source tree, then create a complete OSv image for a given application, based on the application’s Makefile. For more on <code>scripts/build</code>, see <a href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/04/08/makefile/">the recent blog post on the OSv build system</a>.</p>

<h2>Capstan</h2>

<p>The image comes with Capstan pre-installed. Note that to use Capstan, you&rsquo;ll have to run the container with the &mdash;privileged option, as it requires the KVM kernel module. For example, to build and run the iperf application:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
<span class='line-number'>8</span>
<span class='line-number'>9</span>
<span class='line-number'>10</span>
<span class='line-number'>11</span>
<span class='line-number'>12</span>
<span class='line-number'>13</span>
<span class='line-number'>14</span>
<span class='line-number'>15</span>
<span class='line-number'>16</span>
<span class='line-number'>17</span>
<span class='line-number'>18</span>
<span class='line-number'>19</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="nv">$ </span>sudo docker run -it <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  --privileged <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  cloudrouter/osv-builder
</span><span class='line'>bash-4.3# <span class="nb">cd </span>apps/iperf
</span><span class='line'>bash-4.3# capstan build
</span><span class='line'>Building iperf...
</span><span class='line'>Downloading cloudius/osv-base/index.yaml...
</span><span class='line'>154 B / 154 B <span class="o">[=================================================================================================================]</span> 100.00 % 0
</span><span class='line'>Downloading cloudius/osv-base/osv-base.qemu.gz...
</span><span class='line'>20.09 MB / 20.09 MB <span class="o">[=======================================================================================================]</span> 100.00 % 1m27s
</span><span class='line'>Uploading files...
</span><span class='line'>1 / 1 <span class="o">[=========================================================================================================================]</span> 100.00 % bash-4.3# capstan run
</span><span class='line'>Created instance: iperf
</span><span class='line'>OSv v0.19
</span><span class='line'>eth0: 192.168.122.15
</span><span class='line'>------------------------------------------------------------
</span><span class='line'>Server listening on TCP port 5001
</span><span class='line'>TCP window size: 64.0 KByte <span class="o">(</span>default<span class="o">)</span>
</span><span class='line'>------------------------------------------------------------
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Launching an interactive session</h2>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="nv">HOST_BUILD_DIR</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$(</span><span class="nb">pwd</span><span class="k">)</span>/build
</span><span class='line'>docker run -it <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  --volume <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">HOST_BUILD_DIR</span><span class="k">}</span>:/osv/builder <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  cloudrouter/osv-builder
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This will place you into the OSv source clone.  You’ll see the prompt:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>bash-4.3#
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Now, you can work with it as you normally would when working on OSv source.  You can build apps, edit build scripts, and so on. For example, you can run the following commands, once the above <code>docker run</code> commands has been executed, to build and run a tomcat appliance.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>./scripts/build <span class="nv">image</span><span class="o">=</span>tomcat,httpserver
</span><span class='line'>./scripts/run -V
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>The <code>osv</code> Command</h2>

<p><strong>Note</strong> that the commands you run can be prefixed with <code>osv</code>, the source for which is available at <code>assets/osv</code>. For example you can build by:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>docker run <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  --volume <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">HOST_BUILD_DIR</span><span class="k">}</span>:/osv/build <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  osv-builder <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  osv build <span class="nv">image</span><span class="o">=</span>opendaylight
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The <code>osv</code> script, by default, provides the following convenience wrappers:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th align="left"> Command                                     </th>
<th align="left"> Mapping</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left"> build <em>args</em>                                </td>
<td align="left"> scripts/build </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left"> run <em>args</em>                                  </td>
<td align="left"> scripts/run.py</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left"> appliance <em>name</em> <em>components</em> <em>description</em> </td>
<td align="left"> scripts/build-vm-img</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left"> clean                                       </td>
<td align="left"> make clean</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>If any other command is used, it is simply passed on as <code>scripts/$CMD "$@"</code> where <code>$@</code> is the arguments following the command.</p>

<p>You could also run commands as:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>docker run <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  --volume <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">HOST_BUILD_DIR</span><span class="k">}</span>:/osv/build <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  osv-builder <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  ./scripts/build <span class="nv">image</span><span class="o">=</span>opendaylight
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<h2>Building appliance images</h2>

<p>If using the pre-built version from Docker Hub, use <code>cloudrouter/osv-builder</code> instead of <code>osv-builder</code>.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'><span class="nv">HOST_BUILD_DIR</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="k">$(</span><span class="nb">pwd</span><span class="k">)</span>/build
</span><span class='line'>docker run <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  --volume <span class="k">${</span><span class="nv">HOST_BUILD_DIR</span><span class="k">}</span>:/osv/build <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  osv-builder <span class="se">\</span>
</span><span class='line'>  osv appliance zookeeper apache-zookeeper,cloud-init <span class="s2">&quot;Apache Zookeeper on OSv&quot;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>If everything goes well, the images should be available in <code>${HOST_BUILD_DIR}</code>. This will contain appliance images for <a href="http://wiki.qemu.org/KVM">QEMU/KVM</a>, <a href="https://www.virtualbox.org/">Oracle VirtualBox</a>, <a href="https://cloud.google.com/compute/">Google Compute Engine</a> and <a href="https://www.vmware.com/">VMWare</a> Virtual Machine Disk.</p>

<p>Note that we explicitly disable the build of <a href="http://www.vmware.com/products/esxi-and-esx/overview">VMware ESXi</a> images since <code>ovftool</code> is not available.</p>

<h2>Building locally</h2>

<p>As an alternative, you can build locally with a <code>docker build</code> command, using the <a href="https://registry.hub.docker.com/u/cloudrouter/osv-builder/dockerfile/">Dockerfile</a> for osv-builder.</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='sh'><span class='line'>docker build -t osv-builder .
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Then you can use a plain <code>osv-builder</code> image name instead of <code>cloudrouter/osv-builder</code>.</p>

<p>For more information regarding OSv Appliances and pre-built ones, check the <a href="http://osv.io/virtual-appliances/">OSv virtual appliances page</a>.</p>

<h2>Volume Mapping</h2>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th align="left"> Volume      </th>
<th align="left"> Description                                                               </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left"> /osv        </td>
<td align="left"> This directory contains the OSv repository.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left"> /osv/apps   </td>
<td align="left"> The OSv apps directory. Mount this if you are testing local applications.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left"> /osv/build  </td>
<td align="left"> The OSv build directory containing release and standalone directories.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td align="left"> /osv/images </td>
<td align="left"> The OSv image build configurations.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h2>Sending OSv patches</h2>

<p>If you’re following the <a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/osv/wiki/Formatting-and-sending-patches">Formatting and sending patches</a> guide on the OSv web site, just copy your patches into the <code>builder</code> directory in the container, and they’ll show up under your <code>$HOST_BUILD_DIR</code>, ready to be sent to the mailing list.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>With the osv-builder docker image, building your own OSv images is now easier than ever before. If you are looking for a high-performance operating system to run your applications, go ahead and give it a try!</p>

<p>Questions and comments welcome on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev mailing list</a>.</p>

<h2>About the authors</h2>

<p><strong>David</strong> is a product security engineer based in Brisbane, Australia. He currently leads product security efforts for IIX, a software-defined interconnection company. David has been involved in the security industry for the last 15 years. During this time he has found high-impact and novel flaws in dozens of major Java components. He has worked for Red Hat’s security team, led a Chinese startup that failed miserably, and wrote the core aviation meteorology system for the southern hemisphere. In his spare time he tries to stop his two Dachshunds from taking over the house.</p>

<p><strong>Don</strong> is a technical marketing manager for Cloudius Systems, the OSv company. He has written for Linux Weekly News, Linux Journal, and other publications. He co-founded the Linux consulting firm Electric Lichen, which was acquired by VA Linux Systems. Don has served as president and vice president of the Silicon Valley Linux Users Group and on the program committees for Uselinux, Codecon, and LinuxWorld Conference and Expo.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Re-"make"-ing OSv]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/04/08/makefile/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/04/08/makefile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/osv-dev/x-E9YfzDz20">OSv 0.19</a> is out, with a rewrite of the build system. The old OSv build system was fairly complex, but the rewrite makes it simpler and faster.</p>

<h2>Simpler Makefile</h2>

<p>The old OSv build system had several makefiles including each other, playing tricks with the current directory and <code>VPATH</code>, dynamically rewriting makefiles, and running submakes.</p>

<p>The old <code>Makefile</code> was responsible not only for building the kernel, it also built tests, called various Python scripts to build modules for different applications, and carried out other tasks.</p>

<p>In the new build system, there is just one &ldquo;Makefile&rdquo; for building the entire OSv kernel. Everything is in one file, and also better commented.</p>

<h2>Separate kernel building from application building</h2>

<p>In the old build system, we used &ldquo;make&rdquo; to do everything from building the OSv kernel, building various applications, and building images containing OSv and a collection of applications. This complicated the <code>Makefile</code>, and resulted in unexpected build requirements. For example, building OSv always built some Java tests and thus required Maven and a working Internet connection).</p>

<p>In the new system, <code>make</code> only builds the OSv kernel, and <code>scripts/build</code>
build applications and images. In the future, you could use <a href="http://osv.io/capstan/">Capstan</a> instead of <code>scripts/build</code> to make an image that you would like to manage with Capstan.</p>

<p>Most <code>make</code> command lines that worked in the previous build system will
continue to work unchanged with <code>scripts/build</code>. For example:</p>

<pre><code># build image with default OSv application
scripts/build

# build the rogue image
scripts/build image=rogue
# or
scripts/build modules=rogue

# clean kernel and all modules
scripts/build clean

# make parameters can also be given to build
scripts/build mode=debug

# build image with tests, and run them
scripts/build check
</code></pre>

<p>&nbsp;</p>

<p>Additional benefits of this rewrite include:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Faster rebuilds. For example &ldquo;touch loader.cc; scripts/build image=rogue&rdquo;
takes just 6 seconds (14 seconds previously). make after &ldquo;make clean&rdquo;
(with ccache) is just 10 seconds (30 seconds previously).</p></li>
<li><p>It should be fairly easy to add additional
build scripts which will build different types of images using the same
OSv kernel. One popularly requested option is to have the ability to
create a bootfs-only image, without ZFS.</p></li>
<li><p>Some smaller improvements, like more accurate setting of the desired image size <a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/osv/issues/595">(covered in issue #595)</a>, and supporting setting CROSS_PREFIX without also needing to specify ARCH.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>What happened to <code>make test</code>?</h2>

<p>The OSv test are a module like other modules &ndash; they won&rsquo;t be compiled unless someone builds the <code>tests</code> module. They will have a separate Makefile in <code>tests/</code>. The <code>ant</code> and <code>mvn</code> tools, both currently used in our makefile just for building tests, will no longer be run every time the kernel is compiled, but just when the &ldquo;tests&rdquo; module is being built. To build and run the tests:</p>

<pre><code>scripts/build check
</code></pre>

<h2>Try it out</h2>

<p>The good news is that now, running <code>make</code> is faster, and the image build process is simpler and easier to extend. Check it out &mdash; questions and comments welcome on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev mailing list</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Wiki Watch: CloudRouter Images Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/04/03/cloudrouter/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/04/03/cloudrouter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Interested in running the <a href="https://cloudrouter.org/">CloudRouter</a> VMs that we covered in <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/blog/2015/03/31/sdi/">a blog post earlier this week?</a>  Details are available <a href="https://cloudrouter.atlassian.net/wiki/display/CPD/Running+CloudRouter+OSv+Images">on the CloudRouter wiki</a>. (Pre-built images are available <a href="https://repo.cloudrouter.org/">on the CloudRouter site</a>, or you can build one yourself with Capstan.)</p>

<p>Questions on these or any other images are welcome, on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev mailing list</a>.  For more info on working with the CloudRouter project, see <a href="https://cloudrouter.org/community/">the CloudRouter community page</a>.</p>

<p>For future updates, please follow <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Software-defined Interconnection: The Future of Internet Peering, Powered by OpenDaylight and OSv]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/03/31/sdi/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/03/31/sdi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By David Jorm and Don Marti</strong></p>

<p>Most users are aware of cloud computing as a general term behind such trends as &ldquo;Software as a Service,&rdquo; where sites such as Salesforce.com can replace software run by a company IT department, or &ldquo;Infrastructure as a Service&rdquo; where virtual machines rented by the hour can replace conventional servers. But today, the technologies behind the cloud are changing the way that we connect the Internet at the most fundamental level, through Software Defined Interconnection (SDI).</p>

<p><strong>What is SDI?</strong> A lot of manual work goes into hooking up the Internet between providers. The routers that send Internet traffic from one place to another can be configured to use &ldquo;paid transit&rdquo;, where a single provider will route packets to any destination. But the more Internet traffic you’re responsible for, the more you can benefit from another arrangement, called &ldquo;direct interconnection&rdquo; where you set up your company’s routers to directly connect to another company’s. Most networks will always need to buy transit from somebody; the best you can hope for is that a portion of your traffic bypasses the transit provider and is directly delivered to the destination. Maximizing the amount of traffic that is directly peered leads to better performance, lower latency, lower packet loss, and greater security.</p>

<p>Today, most direct interconnection is typically set up manually, with a physical fiber cable connecting one organization’s network to another. Agreements to interconnect and peer are also reached manually, typically via email or face-to-face at peering conferences. When agreement is reached, network admins must ssh in to routers in order to manually configure such peering. It’s not efficient or scalable, and depends on individuals or select groups.</p>

<p>Once an organization has agreed that they want to directly connect with another organization, how do you handle changes to router and switch configuration? Probably the same way you used to manage your httpd.conf back in the 1990s! Network managers ssh in, and update config manually. Some networks have sophisticated management tools, but for many, &ldquo;the state of the router is the canonical state.&rdquo;</p>

<p><img src="http://www.cloudius-systems.com/images/iix_rack.png"
 alt="Software-defined interconnection"></p>

<p><em>Software-defined interconnection, under test in the IIX lab</em></p>

<p>SDI aims to improve all that. The OpenDaylight project is a common platform for network management that facilitates breaking traditional network devices such as switches and routers into separate &ldquo;data plane&rdquo; devices that handle high traffic volume and &ldquo;control plane&rdquo; devices that do management. Because the control plane device, or software-defined networking (SDN) controller, does not have the extreme throughput requirements of the data plane, it’s easy to virtualize.</p>

<p><strong>In the lab today</strong> IIX is currently prototyping this next generation of devices in the lab, while more traditional network gear runs in production. The prototype system uses an <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenFlow">OpenFlow switch</a> for data plane, and a separate OpenDaylight server for control plane. Switches rely on the SDN controller. In the event of an unknown packet, they forward it to the controller.</p>

<p>No configuration changes are needed on the data plane hardware, only on the SDN controller, which can be a virtual machine. OpenDaylight manages both layer 2, switching, and layer 3, routing, and the same OpenDaylight APIs can be used to change configuration at both levels.</p>

<p>OpenDaylight is a pure Java application. It only requires the ability to run a JVM on the virtual machine. For security and ease of management, it can be advantageous to run an individual controller per customer. This means a lightweight, easy-to-manage guest OS is a big advantage. With OSv, IIX can deploy identical simple VMs for each customer, and the OpenDaylight APIs can be used to configure each one appropriately.</p>

<p>OSv’s high performance and low overhead allows for high density of VMs on standard physical hardware. And any compromise or configuration error should only affect one customer, because strong isolation is provided by a standard hypervisor, without the <a href="http://www.projectatomic.io/blog/2014/09/yet-another-reason-containers-don-t-contain-kernel-keyrings/">complex security model of containerization</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion</strong> While Internet applications have gained from cloud technologies, the fundamental lower layers are still coming up to speed. OpenDaylight and OSv are bringing cloud economics to the lower levels of the stack.</p>

<h2>About the authors</h2>

<p><strong>David</strong> is a product security engineer based in Brisbane, Australia. He currently leads product security efforts for IIX, a software-defined interconnection company. David has been involved in the security industry for the last 15 years. During this time he has found high-impact and novel flaws in dozens of major Java components. He has worked for Red Hat&rsquo;s security team, led a Chinese startup that failed miserably, and wrote the core aviation meteorology system for the southern hemisphere. In his spare time he tries to stop his two Dachshunds from taking over the house.</p>

<p><strong>Don</strong> is a technical marketing manager for Cloudius Systems, the OSv company. He has written for Linux Weekly News, Linux Journal, and other publications. He co-founded the Linux consulting firm Electric Lichen, which was acquired by VA Linux Systems. Don has served as president and vice president of the Silicon Valley Linux Users Group and on the program committees for Uselinux, Codecon, and LinuxWorld Conference and Expo.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Seastar: New C++ Framework for Web-scale Workloads]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/02/20/seastar/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-20T06:54:23-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/02/20/seastar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today, we are releasing Seastar, a new open-source C++
framework for extreme high-performance applications
on OSv and Linux. Seastar brings a 5x throughput
improvement to web-scale workloads, at millions of
transactions per second on a single server, and is
optimized for modern physical and virtual hardware.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.seastar-project.org/img/memcache.png" alt="seastar Memcache graph" /></p>

<p><em>Benchmark results are available from the <a href="http://www.seastar-project.org/">new Seastar
project site</a>.</em></p>

<p><strong>Today’s server hardware is <a href="http://danluu.com/new-cpu-features/">substantially different</a> from
the machines for which today’s server software
was written.</strong> Multi-core design and complex
caching now require us to make new assumptions to
get good performance.  And today’s more complex
workloads, where many microservices interact to
fulfil a single user request, are driving down the
latencies required at all layers of the stack. On
new hardware, the performance of standard workloads
depends more on locking and coordination across cores
than on performance of an individual core. And the
full-featured network stack of a conventional OS can
also use a majority of a server’s CPU cycles.</p>

<p><strong>Seastar reaches linear scalability,</strong> as a
function of core count, by taking a shard-per-core
approach. SeaStar tasks do not depend on synchronous
data exchange with other cores which is usually
implemented by compare-exchange and similar locking
schemes. Instead, each core owns its resources (RAM,
NIC queue, CPU) and exchanges async messages with
remote cores. Seastar includes its own user-space
network stack, which runs on top of <a href="http://dpdk.org/">Data Plane
Development Kit</a> (DPDK). All
network communications can take place without system
calls, and no data copying ever occurs. SeaStar is
event-driven and supports writing non-blocking,
asynchronous server code in a straightforward
manner that facilitates debugging and reasoning
about performance.</p>

<p>Seastar is currently focused on high-throughput,
low-latency network applications. For example,
it is useful for NoSQL servers, for data caches
such as memcached, and for high-performance HTTP
serving. Seastar is available today, under the Apache
license version 2.0.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="http://www.seastar-project.org/">Seastar project site</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/seastar">Seastar repository on GitHub</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?hl=en#!forum/seastar-dev">seastar-dev mailing list</a></p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Please follow
<a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a>
on Twitter for updates.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Researching the Future of the Cloud]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/02/02/mikelangelo/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-02T10:54:23-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/02/02/mikelangelo</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Nadav Har&#8217;El</strong></p>

<p>What will the IaaS cloud of the future look like? How can we improve the
hypervisor to reduce the overhead it adds to virtual machines? How can we
improve the operating system on each VM to make it faster, smaller, and
more agile? How do we write applications that run more efficiently and
conveniently on the modern cloud? How can we run on the cloud applications
which traditionally required specialized hardware, such as supercomputers?</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/mikelangelo.png" alt="Project Mikelangelo" /></p>

<p>Cloudius Systems, together with eight leading industry and university
partners, announced this month the <a href="http://mikelangelo-project.eu/">Mikelangelo</a> research project, which
sets out to answer exactly these questions. Mikelangelo is funded by the
European Union&rsquo;s flagship research program, <a href="http://ec.europa.eu/programmes/horizon2020/">&ldquo;Horizon 2020&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p>Cloudius Systems brings to this project two significant technologies:</p>

<p>The first is OSv, our efficient and light-weight operating-system kernel
optimized especially for VMs in the cloud. OSv can run existing Linux
applications, but often with significantly improved performance and lower
memory and disk footprint.</p>

<p>Our second contribution to the cloud of the future is Seastar, a new
framework for writing complex asynchronous applications while achieving
optimal performance on modern machines. Seastar could be used to write
the building blocks of modern user-facing cloud applications, such as
HTTP servers, object caches and NoSQL databases, with staggering
performance: Our prototype implementations already showed a 4-fold
increase in server throughput compared to the commonly used alternatives,
and linear scalability of performance on machines with up to 32 cores.</p>

<p>The other companies which joined us in the Mikelangelo project are
an exciting bunch, and include some ground-breaking European (and global)
cloud researchers and practicioners:</p>

<p>&nbsp;&bull; <a href="http://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/consortium/huawei/">Huawei</a></p>

<p>&nbsp;&bull; <a href="http://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/consortium/ibm/">IBM</a></p>

<p>&nbsp;&bull; <a href="http://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/consortium/intel/">Intel</a></p>

<p>&nbsp;&bull; <a href="http://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/consortium/hlrs/">The University of Stuttgart&rsquo;s supercomputing center (HLRS)</a></p>

<p>&nbsp;&bull; <a href="http://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/consortium/gwdg/">The University of Goettingen&rsquo;s computing center (GWDG)</a></p>

<p>&nbsp;&bull; <a href="http://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/consortium/ben-gurion-university/">Ben-Gurion University</a></p>

<p>&nbsp;&bull; <a href="http://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/consortium/xlab/">XLAB</a>, the coordinator of the project</p>

<p>&nbsp;&bull; <a href="http://www.mikelangelo-project.eu/consortium/pipistrel/">Pipistrel</a>, a light aircraft manufacturer</p>

<p>Pipistrel&rsquo;s intended use case, of moving HPC jobs to the cloud, is
particularly interesting. Pipistrel is an innovative manufacturer of
light aircraft that holds <a href="http://www.pipistrel.si/media/achievements-and-awards">several cool world records</a>, and won NASA&rsquo;s
2011 &ldquo;Green Flight Challenge&rdquo; by building an all-electric airplane
achieving the equivalent of 400 miles per gallon per passenger.
The aircraft design process involves numerous heavy numerical
simulations. If a typical run requires 100 machines for two hours,
running it on the cloud means they would not need to own 100 machines,
and rather just pay for the computer time they use. Moreover, on the
cloud they could just as easily deploy 200 machines, and finish the
job in half the time, for exactly the same price!</p>

<p>Last week, researchers from all these partners met to kick off the
project, and also enjoyed a visit to Ljubljana which, as its name implies,
is a lovely city. The project will span 3 years, but we expect to see some
encouraging results from the project&mdash;and from the individual partners
comprising it&mdash;very soon. The future of the cloud looks very bright!</p>

<p><em>Visit <a href="http://mikelangelo-project.eu/">The Mikelangelo Project&rsquo;s official site</a> for updates.</em></p>

<p><strong>Watch this space (<a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>), or follow
<a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a>
on Twitter, for more links to research in progress.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unikernel Research at the University of Utah]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/01/14/performance-evaluation/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-14T15:54:23-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/01/14/performance-evaluation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ian Briggs, Matt Day, Eric Eide, Yuankai Guo, and
Peter Marheine are conducting performance research
on unikernels, and have thoughtfully posted some
preliminary work on OSv performance.</p>

<p>The team tested OSv for DNS and HTTP, and got some
encouraging results.</p>

<p><a href="http://osv.io/blog/images/http-server-benchmark.png"><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/http-server-benchmark.png" alt="HTTP server comparison" /></a></p>

<p>The lighttpd web server on OSv performs consistently
well up through 5000 requests/second.  And on DNS
tests, Linux can sustain a response rate of about
19000 per second, while OSv can handle approximately 28000 requests per second, with slightly
lower latency.</p>

<p>The preliminary paper is
<a href="http://www.cs.utah.edu/~peterm/prelim-osv-performance.pdf">Performance Evaluation of OSv for Server
Applications</a>
(<a href="http://osv.io/blog/images/prelim-osv-performance.pdf">local copy</a>).</p>

<p>The researchers did run into a bug running OSv
on Xen, so we&rsquo;re all looking forward to helping
them track that down on the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev mailing
list</a>.
In the meantime, watch this space, or follow
<a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a>
on Twitter, for more links to OS research in progress.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSv Meetup Group in Bangalore, India]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/01/07/meetup/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-07T07:54:23-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2015/01/07/meetup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So far, OSv <a href="http://www.meetup.com/OSv-Developer-Meetup/">Meetups</a> have happened in Fremont and San Francisco, California, and Hertzeliya, Israel.  Next week, the Bangalore, India OSv Meetup is happening&mdash;details on the <a href="http://www.meetup.com/OSv-Developer-Meetup-Bangalore/">Bangalore Meetup page</a>.</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/meetup.jpg" alt="attendees" />
<em>Attendees focus on building their applications on OSv in a California meetup last summer</em></p>

<p>The topic for the first meeting, on Sunday January 11, is an OSv code walkthrough.</p>

<p>To get advance notice of future events please join the (California-based) <a href="http://www.meetup.com/OSv-Developer-Meetup/">Meetup group</a> or the new
<a href="http://www.meetup.com/OSv-Developer-Meetup-Bangalore/">OSv Developer Meetup, Bangalore</a>.   For general info, you can follow <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Image Building Tip: Make Clean Without Repeating Yourself]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/12/16/make-clean-dont-repeat-yourself/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-16T21:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/12/16/make-clean-dont-repeat-yourself</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Don Marti</strong></p>

<p>What do we have to do in <code>make clean</code>?  Delete all the files that can be regenerated that we don&rsquo;t need to keep around.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s listed in <code>.gitignore</code>?  All the files that can be regenerated that we don&rsquo;t need to keep around.</p>

<p>Hey, wait a minute. It&rsquo;s not a good idea to repeat yourself, especially for me, since I have to &ldquo;start a project&rdquo; often for demo code.  So here&rsquo;s a way to keep track of all those extre files in one place, with a few lines in Makefile and one handy git command.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Here&rsquo;s the new <code>clean</code> target:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
<span class='line-number'>3</span>
<span class='line-number'>4</span>
<span class='line-number'>5</span>
<span class='line-number'>6</span>
<span class='line-number'>7</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'># Remove anything listed in the .gitignore file.
</span><span class='line'># Remove empty directories because they cannot be versioned.
</span><span class='line'>clean :
</span><span class='line'>        find . -path ./.git -prune -o -print0 | \
</span><span class='line'>        git check-ignore -z --stdin | xargs -0 rm -f
</span><span class='line'>        find . -depth -mindepth 1 -type d -print0 | \
</span><span class='line'>        xargs -0 rmdir --ignore-fail-on-non-empty</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>In this case, we&rsquo;re just running a <code>find</code> on everything except the <code>.git</code> directory, and using the <a href="http://git-scm.com/docs/git-check-ignore">git check-ignore</a> command to see if they&rsquo;re ignorable by git.  If the answer is yes, then they&rsquo;re fine to remove&mdash;so no more keeping track of them in two places.</p>

<p>The second <code>find</code> is just to get rid of empty directories, which Git won&rsquo;t track anyway.  And the <code>-print0</code>, <code>-z</code>, and <code>-0</code> options in both lines are to use null characters between filenames, just to prevent weirdness if you end up with a file with a space in its name.</p>

<p>(To hook your regular Makefile up to build complete VMs, just use <a href="http://osv.io/capstan/">Capstan</a>. Get a complete VM, ready to run on any cloud, in only 7.5 to 9 seconds.)</p>

<h2>What, is that it?</h2>

<p>Fine, have a bonus tip.  If you&rsquo;re a fan of <a href="http://whatcolourisit.scn9a.org/">What colour is it</a>, the site that changes background color to match the current time, here&rsquo;s how to do the same thing on a GNOME desktop:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>gsettings set org.gnome.desktop.background primary-color "#$(date +%H%M%S)"</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>(Those of you on something other than Linux+GNOME, developer desktop tips for your setup are welcome.)</p>

<p><em>For more tips and OSv news, subscribe to this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllow <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSv on the QEMU Advent Calendar]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/12/11/advent/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-11T14:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/12/11/advent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OSv is on the <a href="http://www.qemu-advent-calendar.org/#day-11">QEMU Advent Calendar</a> with a ready-to-download VM image.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.qemu-advent-calendar.org/#day-11"><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/day11.png" alt="day 11" /></a></p>

<p>Not just a demo, it&rsquo;s a fully functional Redis data store with a web management console that you can try with a real Redis application.   There are more fun projects on the QEMU Advent Calendar site, too.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Can someone make a VM that&rsquo;s even smaller than an OSv one?  Looks like the answer is yes.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.qemu-advent-calendar.org/#day-10"><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/day10.png" alt="day 10" /></a></p>

<p>Poor <a href="http://www.nyan.cat/original">Nyan Cat</a>, squashed to just 512 bytes (including a PC speaker version of the music) in the <a href="http://www.qemu-advent-calendar.org/#day-10">Day 10 download</a> from Max Reitz.  There&rsquo;s also vintage retrocomputing, some near-future 64-bit ARM action, and more.  Check it out: <a href="http://www.qemu-advent-calendar.org/">QEMU Advent Calendar</a>.</p>

<p>For the latest cloud and OSv news, subscript to this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or follow <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making Spam Vanish&hellip;in the CLOUD]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/12/04/spamsink/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-04T14:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/12/04/spamsink</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Don Marti</strong></p>

<p>We knew that spammers control a lot of bandwidth, because botnets.  So, for a long time, people thought that fighting spam by just accepting and discarding huge amounts of it would be counterproductive. The spammers get bandwidth for free, and servers are expensive.</p>

<p>There have been some interesting
projects to
try to waste the spammer&rsquo;s bandwidth by fooling the sender into wasting precious bandwidth and CPU by forcing it to retransmit packets, reorder, and retransmit them.</p>

<p>For example, see <a href="http://www.spamcannibal.org/cannibal.cgi">Spam Cannibal</a>. Other spam tarpits focused on a different part of the spam problem: trapping the address-harvesting part of the spam operation.  Address generators would build a dynamic site which has an infinite hierarchy of random pages, each containing a few bogus email addresses and links to more of these fake pages.  An example is <a href="http://www.devin.com/sugarplum/">Sugarplum</a> by Devin Carraway.</p>

<p>Sugarplum created pages such as <a href="this%20randomly%20generated%20page">http://www.devin.com/peaches/lemons</a> and this <a href="http://www.devin.com/peaches/lemons/disentangles/fingerboard">directory of people who want to buy herbal weight loss products</a> (psst. humans. Not really, just more spamtrap addresses. Don&rsquo;t tell the address-harvesting bots.)</p>

<p>But in most cases, for a long time, our only hope for fighting spam was to batten down the hatches.  Assume that the spammers control more computing power and bandwidth than we do, and just do the best we can to filter it.</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/vortex.jpeg" alt="vortex image" /></p>

<p>Is that the best we can do?</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>That was then, this is Cloud</h2>

<p>Is that still true?  Except in high-end &ldquo;fiberhoods,&rdquo; the bandwidth available to end-user machines is stagnant.  Especially upstream bandwidth.  And, much as we like to complain about the security situation on commodity operating systems, it is getting somewhat better.</p>

<p>And cloud computing continues to be built out everywhere.  Now, lots of people have access to cheap or even free cloud VMs.  If you have extra unused cloud capacity, you can use part of it as a spam sink.</p>

<h2>Do spammers still outnumber us?  Let&rsquo;s find out.</h2>

<p>This project is a simple way to build a stand-alone VM that accepts and drops all spam.</p>

<p>Got a free account on a cloud provider, or extra capacity on your hypervisor?   Run a spam sink.  (If you&rsquo;re a cloud provider, you can stick spam sinks on all your spare IP addresses.)</p>

<h2>How to use:</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Build a spamsink VM with &ldquo;capstan build&rdquo; (You can get the Capstan VM-building tool from the <a href="Capstan%20project%20on%20GitHub">https://github.com/cloudius-systems/capstan</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Deploy to your favorite private or public cloud.</p></li>
<li><p>Point some MX records and spamtrap addresses at it.  You can run Sugarplum (above) to generate as many random addresses as you want.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>To try it out locally:</h2>

<p>Build and run: <code>capstan build &amp;&amp; capstan run -n bridge</code></p>

<p>OSv will print the IP address.  In another terminal, point the smtpsend client at it:</p>

<p><code>./smtpsend -n 100</code></p>

<h2>On GitHub</h2>

<p>A spamsink <a href="https://github.com/dmarti/spamsink">GitHub repository</a> is up.  Pull requests welcome.</p>

<p>For the latest cloud and OSv news, subscript to this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or follow <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>

<p><em>Vortex image: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Vortex_in_draining_bottle_of_water.jpg">Robert D Anderson for Wikimedia Commons</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Containers, Containers, Containers! More Options for the Cloud]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/12/02/docker-rocket/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-02T14:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/12/02/docker-rocket</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By <a href="https://twitter.com/DorLaor/">Dor Laor</a></strong></p>

<p>Everybody who uses containers has probably heard about <a href="https://coreos.com/blog/rocket">Rocket</a> by now. What does this <strike>fork</strike> re-implementation mean to the Docker community? Let’s dive in.</p>

<p>The Docker technology has disrupted the cloud and datacenter field for the past year. The speed of penetration was amazing and unmatched in the industry. I can’t think of a similar case for such fast-paced adoption of the concept. Neither AWS, OpenStack, nor virtualization were adopted that fast. What made it that attractive for our community to adopt?</p>

<p>Container technology was there for a lot of years. Even before containers, there has always been similar functionality, like Unix’s <code>chroot</code>. However, Docker really changed the game with straightforward simplicity and usability. Docker contributed the following:</p>

<ol>
<li><p> A basic one-liner command line: <code>docker run</code>. It masked out all of the LXC complexities and even downloaded the image if needed.</p></li>
<li><p>Straightforward image structure: It’s as simple as a directory.</p></li>
<li><p>A public image repository, <a href="https://hub.docker.com/">Docker Hub</a>, where you can stash your images for future download, and employ an application-market concept.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>Docker had become the hottest thing in tech, sometimes way too hot for reality (otherwise, why would one deploy Docker in a VM, incurring two tiers of management pain?). Beyond Google and AWS, even mighty Microsoft wanted a piece of the pie. We couldn’t believe our eyes, what an amazing meritocracy (no sarcasm). All the vendors of the world unite around one simple format.</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/meritocracy.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>Yesterday CoreOS released a fork-like bomb in the form of Rocket. The reason
is the very thing that makes Docker attractive, its simplicity, is also a disadvantage since it’s too complex to harness for security, SLA and diverse workloads.  Apparently CoreOS didn’t manage to get the Docker team to change the mainline code for it.  I guess it’s more than a NIH thing (Not Invented Here) but some limitation of its structure.</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/fight-time.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>This container diversity was expected although it saddens me to see it become an ugly fight:</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/docker-thread.png" alt="Twitter thread" /></p>

<p>We believe that CoreOS has the upper hand when it comes to technology. Managing containers is straightforward, but these folks have the vehicle for deploying them. In addition they wrote cool distributed tools such as <code>etcd</code> and <code>fleet</code>. So while Docker controls the hub and the format, CoreOS leverages it to gain actual users (PR aside&hellip;)</p>

<p>There is nothing to fear about Docker momentum, but it has finally met a reality factor and such competition is positive for innovation and speed as well. With all the fuss around Docker, lots of good features like LXC SLA, and buildpacks (the way Heroku and Cloud Foundry handle them) were dropped in the race for Docker compatibility. It was a nice surprise to see that great minds think alike, and just as Rocket uses <a href="https://github.com/coreos/rocket">several phases</a> in container creation, we do the same for OSv. We create an image by spinning up an empty VM (on any given hypervisor) that formats our ZFS filesystem and afterwards listens on ‘nc’ (netcat) to receive a stream of files from the host.</p>

<p>One of the best things about OSv is that we enjoy the best of all worlds. On one hand, we are a library OS, as small as a single container, usually just a kernel, a runtime and an app. An OSv VM can weigh only 20MB, smaller than most containers. On the other hand, we leverage all of the hypervisor features, including live migration, multiple guest kernels on the same host, resource hotplug, isolation, SLA and more.</p>

<p>Let the battle continue as we collect the best of breed features and embrace them as we’ve done with <a href="http://osv.io/capstan/">Capstan</a>, with our <a href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/08/28/wiki-watch-cloud-init/">cloud-init integration</a>, with our <a href="http://osv.io/manageability/">RESTful APIs</a> and more.</p>

<p><em>For the latest cloud and OSv news, subscript to this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or follow <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSv Meetup at EBLUG: Intro Talk and Demo]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/17/eblug/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T16:54:23-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/17/eblug</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Don Marti</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://osv.io/">OSv</a> is the simple, fast OS platform designed to run one application in the cloud, without the complexity of old-school OSs with their local users, permissions, and sevices.  Come see what it&rsquo;s all about, and enjoy free food and drink from East Bay LUG sponsor, Hurricane Electric.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.eblug.org/"><img src="http://www.eblug.org/images/eblugdev-logo-transparent-75px.png" alt="EBLUG logo" /></a></p>

<p><strong>Who:</strong> Don Marti, OSv demo monkey</p>

<p><strong>What:</strong> Introduction to OSv (with live 9-second build demo!)</p>

<p><strong>Where:</strong> <a href="http://www.eblug.org/index.html">East Bay LUG, Fremont, California, USA</a></p>

<p><strong>When:</strong> 7pm Wednesday, November 19, 2014</p>

<p><strong>Why:</strong>  See the new dedicated cloud OS, without the big travel budget</p>

<p>Please join us for the next <a href="http://www.eblug.org/index.html">EBLUG meeting</a>, co-located with the OSv <a href="http://www.meetup.com/OSv-Developer-Meetup/">Meetup group</a>, and get a rapid introduction to OSv, how it works, and where it&rsquo;s going.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re not already a member of the OSv <a href="http://www.meetup.com/OSv-Developer-Meetup/">Meetup group</a>, please join.  For general questions on OSv, please join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev mailing list</a>.  You can get general updates by subscribing to this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SSH Tip: Connecting to a Private Network Without Trusting the Bastion Host]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/17/ssh-without-trusting-bastion-host/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T14:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/17/ssh-without-trusting-bastion-host</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Nadav Har&#8217;El</strong></p>

<p>In a typical lab network configuration, one cannot just <code>ssh</code> or <code>scp</code> to the hosts behind the firewall (our company calls them after characters from Norse mythology: Loki, Muninn and friends).  Instead, you need to ssh to a bastion host, and from there connect to the internal systems.</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/ssh-user.jpeg" alt="ssh user" /><br><em>an ssh user connecting using a bastion host</em></p>

<p>One can automate these two steps, with a command like</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>ssh -t bastion.example.com ssh loki.lab.example.com</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And I guess some of you are already doing that. But this only works for ssh, not scp. One can do scp through an &ldquo;ssh tunnel&rdquo;, but this is really ugly to set up every time and to use.</p>

<p>There is also a securty hole in this approach, because anyone who breaks into <code>bastion</code> (which is an external machine and thus exposed to the Internet) can then ssh from there to all the internal machines, or even hijack already-running ssh sessions.</p>

<p>I finally found a much better solution, much easier to use and much more secure.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Just add to your <code>~/.ssh/config</code> the following incantation:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>Host *.lab
</span><span class='line'>        ProxyCommand ssh -q bastion.example.com nc `basename %h .lab` 22</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>And now, you can <code>ssh</code> or <code>scp</code> directly to <code>loki.lab</code>, or <code>muninn.lab</code> or whatever, without any hassles, as if Loki and Muninn are actual machines on your LAN.</p>

<p>This trick works like this: To connect to the remote host, ssh normally just connects a socket to port 22 of the remote host. When the &ldquo;ProxyCommand&rdquo; is set, this command is used instead. The command above will ssh to <code>bastion.example.com</code> and from there connect (using <code>nc</code>) to loki&rsquo;s port 22. Your own ssh will do the ssh protocol with Loki over this connection.</p>

<p>This solution, beyond being extremely convenient, also has an interesting security feature:  we&rsquo;ll no longer need to trust <code>bastion.example.com</code>. The classic &ldquo;ssh from your laptop to <code>bastion</code> to <code>loki</code>&rdquo; solution suffered from a problem that if someone broke into <code>bastion</code>, they could also break into <code>loki</code> &ndash; by using the private keys stored on <code>bastion</code>, or by hijacking the second leg of the ssh chain (and possibly injecting whatever commands it wanted into this session!). With this new solution, <code>bastion</code> is just acting as a stupid pipe for encypted data between my laptop and Loki &ndash; it cannot hijack the connection, and it doesn&rsquo;t have any private keys needed to initiate a connection to Loki on its own.</p>

<p>For more tips and OSv news, subscript to this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllow <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>

<p><strong>Photo:</strong> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/dfectuoso17/7013054091/">Security Hacker</a> by Santiago Zavala</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSv Early Access Private Beta]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/13/osv-private-beta/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-13T08:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/13/osv-private-beta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cloudius Systems is introducing an early access version of OSv, the lightweight open-source OS optimized for large cloud workloads, on November 13.  <a href="http://osv.io/beta-release/">Beta program information</a> is now available.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.cloudius-systems.com/images/mouse.jpeg" alt="lab mouse" /></p>

<p>OSv can be used to minimize latency and reduce TCO for many workloads, especially horizontally scaled ones. The software is available as ready-to-run virtual machine images pre-configured to run popular NoSQL data stores such as Redis and Apache Cassandra, as well as in source code form.</p>

<p>“OSv lets you take a project from a developer’s IDE to a flexible, multi-server deployment much faster,” said Dor Laor, CEO of Cloudius Systems.  “As customers require more and more throughput at lower and lower operating cost, we enable developers to use the agility of containers along with the proven security and management features known for in virtual machines.”</p>

<p>Cloudius Systems’ early access release features an expanded Web API for management, along with performance improvements that increase efficiency, with an up to a 3.9x throughput gain. Unlike conventional operating systems with their diverse configuration files and complex user and memory management, OSv is designed to provide the minimum OS needed to run a single application at maximum performance in the cloud.</p>

<p>&ldquo;OSv was designed with virtualization in mind,” said Cloudius Systems CTO, Avi Kivity.  “The OS overhead is minimized by a reduction of context switches, data copies, and inefficient constructs such as spinlocks.&rdquo; OSv virtual machines can be as small as 20MB, far smaller than Docker containers, and boot in less than one second.</p>

<h2><a href="http://www.cloudius-systems.com/images/mouse.jpeg">Sign up for the OSv beta</a></h2>

<p>You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.  Hope to see you at the show.</p>

<p>Photo: <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Lab_mouse_mg_3216.jpg">Rama for Wikimedia Commons</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Stage Thursday at Amazon re:Invent]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/12/amazon/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-12T08:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/12/amazon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;re at the Amazon re:Invent show, don&rsquo;t miss <a href="https://www.portal.reinvent.awsevents.com/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=9806">3rd Annual Startup Launches moderated by Werner Vogels</a>. Cloudius Systems CEO Dor Laor will be there, to talk about&hellip;.but we can&rsquo;t tell you that yet.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Who:</strong> Amazon.com CTO, Dr. Werner Vogels. and five guests</p></li>
<li><p><strong>What:</strong> Learn how innovative new startups use the AWS cloud.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Where:</strong> Level 2 &ndash; Titian 2306</p></li>
<li><p><strong>When:</strong> Thursday, Nov 13, 4:30 PM &ndash; 5:15 PM</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Why:</strong> Knowledge, plus special discounts on new products and services.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>If you can&rsquo;t wait, come over to K14 in the exhibit hall for an OSv demo.
We&rsquo;ve got some <a href="http://www.mcmelectronics.com/product/83-16333RK">Raspberry Pi media kits</a> to give away (to especially intense cloud users who need some real hardware to restore balance to their lives.)</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/kiosk.png" alt="demo pod" /><br><em>Unikernels don&rsquo;t need big heavyweight booths.</em></p>

<p>You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.  Hope to see you at the show.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raspberry Pi at Amazon Re:invent]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/09/rpi/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-09T11:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/09/rpi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Want to see us build a virtual machine for the Amazon cloud at the <a href="https://reinvent.awsevents.com/">re:Invent show</a>?  Come on over to our booth (K14) and we&rsquo;ll show you.  It&rsquo;s simple to add a virtual appliance build step to any application build.</p>

<p>Well, that took nine seconds.  What else can we do?  How about a hardware giveaway?  Since your virtual machines are going to take so little of your time, you should have plenty of time to play with a fun hardware kit.</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/blog/images/rpi.jpeg" alt="Raspberry Pi media kit" /></p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve got some <a href="http://www.mcmelectronics.com/product/83-16333RK">Raspberry Pi media kits</a> to give away.  Not just the board, this kit includes</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Raspberry Pi Model B+ Board</p></li>
<li><p>8GB Operating System microSD Card</p></li>
<li><p>Multicomp Black B+ Case</p></li>
<li><p>Raspberry Pi Power Supply</p></li>
<li><p>Wi-Pi Wireless Adapter</p></li>
<li><p>3&#8217; HDMi Cable</p></li>
<li><p>7&#8217; Ethernet Cable</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Just the thing for a home media center, or a starting point for a more ambitious project such as a <a href="http://www.retrobuiltgames.com/porta-pi-arcade-help/porta-pi-software-os-download/">vintage arcade</a>.</p>

<p>Amazon re:Invent is sold out, but you can <a href="http://reinvent.awsevents.com/livestream-reg.html">sign up for streaming</a> if you&rsquo;re not able to make it.</p>

<p>You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.  Hope to see you at the show.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSv 0.14 Alpha Includes Management Dashboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/03/dashboard/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T21:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/03/dashboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Tzach Livyatan</strong></p>

<p>We are pleased to announce the OSv 0.14 Alpha Release.</p>

<p>This is the first release to include the dashboard, a  browser-based UI for OSv and virtual appliance status.</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/images/dashboard.png" alt="OSv dashboard" /></p>

<p>The dashboard includes (among other features):</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Main tab with Memory, CPU, Disk</p></li>
<li><p>Thread tab with interactive visualization of thread status and thread usage.
You can select and search for particular thread by name.</p></li>
<li><p>Trace tab, including frequency for each tracepoint. Selection by name and search are available.</p></li>
<li><p>JVM tab for basic JVM information including memory and GC, when a JVM is installed.</p></li>
<li><p>Virtual Appliance tab for information relevant to the particular appliance.
Tabs for Cassandra and Tomcat are currently  available, with more to come.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>To build the dashboard, just includes httpserver in
the module list.  For example:</p>

<figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ make -j 4 image=cassandra,httpserver</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>Once the appliance is running, the dashboard is available on port 8000 by default.  (You can change the port using <a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/osv/wiki/cloud-init">cloud-init</a>.)</p>

<p>The <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/osv-dev/tyFGw7NRudA">full 0.14 release announcement</a> is available on the osv-dev mailing list.
You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
