<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Capstan | OSv Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/categories/capstan/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.osv.io//github/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-14T08:38:57+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.osv.io//github/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cloudius Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speed Run: Running 4 Virtual Appliances on Your Laptop in 5 Seconds Overall]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/09/14/how-fast-can-you-run-4-vm/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-14T09:30:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/09/14/how-fast-can-you-run-4-vm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Dor Laor, Tzach Livyatan</strong></p>

<p>In the following demo, Dor is running 4 different OSv base virtual appliances
on his laptop:</p>

<ul>
<li>Redis</li>
<li>Tomcat</li>
<li>MySQL</li>
<li>Cassandra</li>
</ul>


<p>Each virtual appliance is a full–blown VM, each with a pre-integrated
cloud application, and each launched without terminating the others.</p>

<!-- more -->




<script type="text/javascript" src="https://asciinema.org/a/11914.js" id="asciicast-11914" async></script>


<p>As you can see, application startup time takes between sub-second
(Redis) to a few seconds (Cassandra) depending on the application.
The hypervisor plus OS part of the boot time is less than a second for all cases.</p>

<p>Want more info on Capstan and related topics?  Join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev mailing list</a>.  You can get regular OSv updates by subscribing to this blog&rsquo;s feed, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running Clojure on OSv: Easier With a New Capstan Template]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/07/27/capstan-lein-template/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-27T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/07/27/capstan-lein-template</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Clojure developers usually do not care too much about the underlying OS.
The low-level differences between Linux, Mac OS, and even Microsoft Windows are abstracted away by the JVM.</p>

<p>When deploying Clojure code on the cloud, there used to be one default choice &ndash; Linux.
But Linux
<a href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/07/21/generic-os-is-dead/">is not an ideal OS</a>
for pure cloud services.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/osv">OSv</a> is a new, open source OS, designed specifically for the cloud.  Since OSv supports the standard JVM, it is ideal for running Clojure applications on the cloud.  And the same configuration applies to building VMs for any cloud: public clouds such as Amazon&rsquo;s and Google&rsquo;s, private clouds based on VMware or KVM, or public and private OpenStack.</p>

<p>Porting a Clojure application to OSv was already
<a href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/04/22/riemann-on-osv/">pretty easy</a>, but
now it&rsquo;s even easier.  This blog post describes a new <a href="https://github.com/tzach/capstan-lein-plugin">lein template</a> for OSv.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Usage</h2>

<p>Capstan works together with the <a href="http://leiningen.org/">Leinigen</a> build tool.</p>

<p>First, create a new project skeleton.
<code>
lein new capstan new-app
</code></p>

<p>Now, you can run <a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/capstan">Capstan</a> to
run your project on an a OSv VM.</p>

<p><code>
cd new-app
capstan run
</code></p>

<p>The template takes care of creating the project skeleton, including the Capstanfile.  When this is done, you can use Capstan directly to build a new OSv VM, deploy it on the cloud, or upload it to the public repository.</p>

<script type="text/javascript" src="https://asciinema.org/a/11068.js"
id="asciicast-11068" async="" data-speed="2" data-autoplay="1"
ata-size="medium"></script>


<p></p></p>

<p>For more info on Capstan and other OSv subjects, please join
the
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev mailing list</a>.<br/>
You can get updates on by subscribing to the <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">OSv blog RSS feed</a> or following <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Is the Most Popular OSv Virtual Appliance?]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/07/01/s3stat/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-01T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/07/01/s3stat</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Tzach Livyatan</strong></p>

<p>(Spoiler: It&rsquo;s Apache Tomcat.)</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/capstan">Capstan</a> is a tool for rapidly building and running applications on OSv.
As with Docker, Capstan users can download and run images from a public repository.
We chose to implement our public Capstan repository using <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/s3/">Amazon S3</a>.</p>

<p>Amazon S3  gives us the flexibility and security we need, but by default it&rsquo;s missing a critical feature: download statistics.
This statistics are very interesting to us, to evaluate which of the Capstan virtual appliances are more popular.  Fortunately, there is an easy way to gather the stats we need.</p>

<p>After a short tools survey, we choose <a href="http://www.s3stat.com/">s3stat</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.s3stat.com/">s3stat</a> is a cloud-based service which can follow an S3 bucket, and visualize download statistics, by file, country, browser day, or otherwise.
The price makes sense, and it is super easy to enable.</p>

<p><img src="/images/s3stat_chart.png" alt="s3stat chart" /></p>

<p>So what are the results? (drum roll&hellip;.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/images/s3stat_files.png" alt="s3stat files" /></p>

<p>Omitting Capstan download of capstan index.yaml files, which Capstan does for every repository search, the most popular images are the base images for OSv and OSv + Java.
That make sense because these two images will be used by anyone who wants to build a local OSv application, running a native or Java application.</p>

<p>Virtual appliances comes right after, with (drums again&hellip;.) <strong>Tomcat</strong>, <strong>Cassandra</strong>, <strong>Memcached</strong> on the podium (Tomcat wins the Gold).
These are all very early results, but we will keep using s3stat to follow Capstan image downloads.</p>

<p><img src="/images/s3stat_map.png" alt="s3stat map" /></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bridged Networking With Capstan]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/05/07/capstan-bridge/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-07T18:37:05+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/05/07/capstan-bridge</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Don Marti</strong></p>

<p>New versions of <a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/capstan">Capstan</a> are making it simpler to run OSv virtual machines in a production configuration, by adding more control of network options.  A useful new feature, which helps deal with the <a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/osv/wiki/Running-OSv-image-under-KVM-QEMU">details of bringing up networking</a>, is the <code>-n</code> option.</p>

<p>By default, Capstan starts up KVM/QEMU with user networking:</p>

<p><code>
 -netdev user,id=un0,net=192.168.122.0/24,host=192.168.122.1
</code></p>

<p>(That&rsquo;s from <code>ps ax | grep qemu</code>, which you can run
to see the qemu-system-x86_64 command that Capstan
is executing for you.)</p>

<p>But there are many more <a href="http://www.linux-kvm.org/page/Networking">networking options</a> for QEMU/KVM.  The basic user networking, which does not require root access to start up, is good for development and simple tasks.  But for production use, where you need to get your VM on a network where it&rsquo;s available from other VMs or from the outside, you&rsquo;ll need bridged networking.  (See your Linux distribution or hypervisor documentation for the details of creating a virtual or public bridge device.)</p>

<p>If you invoke <code>capstan run</code> with the <code>-n bridge</code> option, you&rsquo;ll get QEMU running with:</p>

<p><code>
-netdev bridge,id=hn0,br=virbr0,helper=/usr/libexec/qemu-bridge-helper
</code></p>

<p>If you have a specific bridge device to connect to, you can use the <code>-b</code> option with the name of the bridge device.  The default is <code>virbr0</code>, but you can also set up a public bridge, usually <code>br0</code>, that&rsquo;s bridged to a physical network interface on the host.</p>

<h1>Other hypervisors</h1>

<p>Don&rsquo;t feel left out if you have a different hypervisor.  Capstan also handles bridged networking on VirtualBox, with the rest of the supported hypervisors coming soon.   The fact that the syntax is the same is going to be a big time-saver for those of us who have to do testing and demos on multiple systems&mdash;no more dealing with arcane commands that are different from system to system.</p>

<p>For more on Capstan and networking, please join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev mailing list on Google Groups</a>.  You can get updates by subscribing to this blog&rsquo;s feed, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Riemann - a Clojure Application on OSv]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/04/22/riemann-on-osv/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-22T19:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.osv.io//github/blog/2014/04/22/riemann-on-osv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Tzach Livyatan</strong></p>

<p>Clojure applications run on the JVM, so they&rsquo;re usually simple to run on OSv.  We have <a href="https://github.com/tzach/capstan-example-clojure">hello world in Clojure</a> running, but this time I wanted to port a real, non-toy, Clojure application. I chose <a href="http://riemann.io">Riemann</a>, a widely-used application for aggregating system events (and more).</p>

<p>I used <a href="http://osv.io/capstan/">Capstan</a>, a tool for building and running applications on OSv.  Jump to the end <a href="https://github.com/tzach/riemann">result</a>, or follow the steps I took:</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Following the Capstan guideline, I added a <a href="https://github.com/tzach/riemann/blob/master/Capstanfile">Capstanfile</a> to the project.  Here are the parts of Capstanfile you need to know about:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Set the base image. In this case I chose a base image with Java (open-jdk)
<code>
base: cloudius/osv-openjdk
</code></p></li>
<li><p>Build the jar file, taking advantage of the <code>lein uberjar</code> command, which packages the application with all dependencies into one jar file.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>```</p>

<pre><code>build: lein uberjar
</code></pre>

<p><code>
  * Copy the build artifacts to the base image, producing a new image:
</code>
files:
  /riemann.jar: ./target/riemann-0.2.5-SNAPSHOT-standalone.jar
  /riemann.config: ./riemann.config
```</p>

<p>I also copy the config file, which Riemann will look for.</p>

<ul>
<li>The run command for the VM is executed when the VM starts.
<code>
cmdline: /java.so -jar /riemann.jar
</code></li>
</ul>


<p>That&rsquo;s it. Done with the Capstanfile.</p>

<p><strong>Let&rsquo;s test it!</strong>
```</p>

<blockquote><p>capstan run
WARN [2014-04-13 14:11:22,029] Thread-9 &ndash; riemann.core &ndash; instrumentation service caught
java.io.IOException: Cannot run program &ldquo;hostname&rdquo;: error=0, vfork failed</p>

<pre><code>at java.lang.ProcessBuilder.start(ProcessBuilder.java:1041)
at java.lang.Runtime.exec(Runtime.java:617)
at clojure.java.shell$sh.doInvoke(shell.clj:116)
at clojure.lang.RestFn.invoke(RestFn.java:408)
</code></pre>

<p><code>
No luck.  It turns out that Riemann is using
</code>
(sh &ldquo;hostname&rdquo;)
```</p></blockquote>

<p>which uses vfork to run a child process. On any OS its not very efficient to fork just to get the hostname, and on current OSv it simply won&rsquo;t work. To bypass the problem, I replace this call with:</p>

<p><code>
(.getHostName (java.net.InetAddress/getLocalHost))
</code>
which uses a Java <code>getHostName</code>.</p>

<p><strong>Let&rsquo;s try again</strong>
```sh</p>

<blockquote><p>capstan run
```
This time it works, but how do I test it and connect to it?</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Let&rsquo;s use Capstan port forwarding</strong>
<code>sh
capstan run -f 5555:5555 -f 5556:5556
</code>
This will  forward host ports 5555 and 5556 to the corresponding ports on the OSv VM.</p>

<p><strong>Success :)</strong></p>

<p>Now we can switch to another terminal and run:
<code>sh
riemann-health
</code>
to generate traffic for Riemann
and
<code>sh
riemann-dash
</code>
to launch a Riemann web GUI.  Here is how it looks:</p>

<p><img src="/images/riemann_on_osv.png" alt="&quot;Riemann GUI" /> <i>riemann-dash</i></p>

<p>Now we&rsquo;re ready to do further stress testing.  If you do find any problem, or have any question, you&rsquo;re invited to join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev list</a> and ask, or post an issue to the <a href="https://github.com/tzach/riemann">GitHub repository</a>.</p>

<p>&mdash; <a href="https://twitter.com/TzachL">Tzach Livyatan</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
