<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Release | OSv Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/categories/release/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://osv.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-17T14:53:21-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://osv.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cloudius Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SSH Tip: Connecting to a Private Network Without Trusting the Bastion Host]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/17/ssh-without-trusting-bastion-host/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T14:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/17/ssh-without-trusting-bastion-host</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Nadav Har'El</strong></p>

<p>In a typical lab network configuration, one cannot just <code>ssh</code> or <code>scp</code> to the hosts behind the firewall (our company calls them after characters from Norse mythology: Loki, Muninn and friends).  Instead, you need to ssh to a bastion host, and from there connect to the internal systems.</p>

<p><img src="/images/ssh-user.jpeg" alt="ssh user" /><br><em>an ssh user connecting using a bastion host</em></p>

<p>One can automate these two steps, with a command like</p>

<p>```</p>

<pre><code>ssh -t bastion.example.com ssh loki.lab.example.com
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>And I guess some of you are already doing that. But this only works for ssh, not scp. One can do scp through an &ldquo;ssh tunnel&rdquo;, but this is really ugly to set up every time and to use.</p>

<p>There is also a securty hole in this approach, because anyone who breaks into <code>bastion</code> (which is an external machine and thus exposed to the Internet) can then ssh from there to all the internal machines, or even hijack already-running ssh sessions.</p>

<p>I finally found a much better solution, much easier to use and much more secure.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Just add to your <code>~/.ssh/config</code> the following incantation:</p>

<p>```
Host *.lab</p>

<pre><code>    ProxyCommand ssh -q bastion.example.com nc `basename %h .lab` 22
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>And now, you can <code>ssh</code> or <code>scp</code> directly to <code>loki.lab</code>, or <code>muninn.lab</code> or whatever, without any hassles, as if Loki and Muninn are actual machines on your LAN.</p>

<p>This trick works like this: To connect to the remote host, ssh normally just connects a socket to port 22 of the remote host. When the &ldquo;ProxyCommand&rdquo; is set, this command is used instead. The command above will ssh to <code>bastion.example.com</code> and from there connect (using <code>nc</code>) to loki&rsquo;s port 22. Your own ssh will do the ssh protocol with Loki over this connection.</p>

<p>This solution, beyond being extremely convenient, also has an interesting security feature:  we&rsquo;ll no longer need to trust <code>bastion.example.com</code>. The classic &ldquo;ssh from your laptop to <code>bastion</code> to <code>loki</code>&rdquo; solution suffered from a problem that if someone broke into <code>bastion</code>, they could also break into <code>loki</code> &ndash; by using the private keys stored on <code>bastion</code>, or by hijacking the second leg of the ssh chain (and possibly injecting whatever commands it wanted into this session!). With this new solution, <code>bastion</code> is just acting as a stupid pipe for encypted data between my laptop and Loki &ndash; it cannot hijack the connection, and it doesn&rsquo;t have any private keys needed to initiate a connection to Loki on its own.</p>

<p>For more tips and OSv news, subscript to this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllow <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>

<p><strong>Photo:</strong> <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/dfectuoso17/7013054091/">Security Hacker</a> by Santiago Zavala</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSv Early Access Private Beta]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/13/osv-private-beta/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-13T08:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/13/osv-private-beta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cloudius Systems is introducing an early access version of OSv, the lightweight open-source OS optimized for large cloud workloads, on November 13.  <a href="http://osv.io/beta-release/">Beta program information</a> is now available.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.cloudius-systems.com/images/mouse.jpeg" alt="lab mouse" /></p>

<p>OSv can be used to minimize latency and reduce TCO for many workloads, especially horizontally scaled ones. The software is available as ready-to-run virtual machine images pre-configured to run popular NoSQL data stores such as Redis and Apache Cassandra, as well as in source code form.</p>

<p>“OSv lets you take a project from a developer’s IDE to a flexible, multi-server deployment much faster,” said Dor Laor, CEO of Cloudius Systems.  “As customers require more and more throughput at lower and lower operating cost, we enable developers to use the agility of containers along with the proven security and management features known for in virtual machines.”</p>

<p>Cloudius Systems’ early access release features an expanded Web API for management, along with performance improvements that increase efficiency, with an up to a 3.9x throughput gain. Unlike conventional operating systems with their diverse configuration files and complex user and memory management, OSv is designed to provide the minimum OS needed to run a single application at maximum performance in the cloud.</p>

<p>&ldquo;OSv was designed with virtualization in mind,” said Cloudius Systems CTO, Avi Kivity.  “The OS overhead is minimized by a reduction of context switches, data copies, and inefficient constructs such as spinlocks.&rdquo; OSv virtual machines can be as small as 20MB, far smaller than Docker containers, and boot in less than one second.</p>

<h2><a href="http://www.cloudius-systems.com/images/mouse.jpeg">Sign up for the OSv beta</a></h2>

<p>You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.  Hope to see you at the show.</p>

<p>Photo: <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Lab_mouse_mg_3216.jpg">Rama for Wikimedia Commons</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Stage Thursday at Amazon re:Invent]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/12/amazon/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-12T08:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/12/amazon</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you&rsquo;re at the Amazon re:Invent show, don&rsquo;t miss <a href="https://www.portal.reinvent.awsevents.com/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=9806">3rd Annual Startup Launches moderated by Werner Vogels</a>. Cloudius Systems CEO Dor Laor will be there, to talk about&hellip;.but we can&rsquo;t tell you that yet.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Who:</strong> Amazon.com CTO, Dr. Werner Vogels. and five guests</p></li>
<li><p><strong>What:</strong> Learn how innovative new startups use the AWS cloud.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Where:</strong> Level 2 &ndash; Titian 2306</p></li>
<li><p><strong>When:</strong> Thursday, Nov 13, 4:30 PM &ndash; 5:15 PM</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Why:</strong> Knowledge, plus special discounts on new products and services.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>If you can&rsquo;t wait, come over to K14 in the exhibit hall for an OSv demo.
We&rsquo;ve got some <a href="http://www.mcmelectronics.com/product/83-16333RK">Raspberry Pi media kits</a> to give away (to especially intense cloud users who need some real hardware to restore balance to their lives.)</p>

<p><img src="/images/kiosk.png" alt="demo pod" /><br><em>Unikernels don&rsquo;t need big heavyweight booths.</em></p>

<p>You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.  Hope to see you at the show.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Raspberry Pi at Amazon Re:invent]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/09/rpi/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-09T11:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/09/rpi</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Want to see us build a virtual machine for the Amazon cloud at the <a href="https://reinvent.awsevents.com/">re:Invent show</a>?  Come on over to our booth (K14) and we&rsquo;ll show you.  It&rsquo;s simple to add a virtual appliance build step to any application build.</p>

<p>Well, that took nine seconds.  What else can we do?  How about a hardware giveaway?  Since your virtual machines are going to take so little of your time, you should have plenty of time to play with a fun hardware kit.</p>

<p><img src="/images/rpi.jpeg" alt="Raspberry Pi media kit" /></p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve got some <a href="http://www.mcmelectronics.com/product/83-16333RK">Raspberry Pi media kits</a> to give away.  Not just the board, this kit includes</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Raspberry Pi Model B+ Board</p></li>
<li><p>8GB Operating System microSD Card</p></li>
<li><p>Multicomp Black B+ Case</p></li>
<li><p>Raspberry Pi Power Supply</p></li>
<li><p>Wi-Pi Wireless Adapter</p></li>
<li><p>3' HDMi Cable</p></li>
<li><p>7' Ethernet Cable</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Just the thing for a home media center, or a starting point for a more ambitious project such as a <a href="http://www.retrobuiltgames.com/porta-pi-arcade-help/porta-pi-software-os-download/">vintage arcade</a>.</p>

<p>Amazon re:Invent is sold out, but you can <a href="http://reinvent.awsevents.com/livestream-reg.html">sign up for streaming</a> if you&rsquo;re not able to make it.</p>

<p>You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.  Hope to see you at the show.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSv 0.14 Alpha Includes Management Dashboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/03/dashboard/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-03T21:10:31-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/11/03/dashboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Tzach Livyatan</strong></p>

<p>We are pleased to announce the OSv 0.14 Alpha Release.</p>

<p>This is the first release to include the dashboard, a  browser-based UI for OSv and virtual appliance status.</p>

<p><img src="http://osv.io/images/dashboard.png" alt="OSv dashboard" /></p>

<p>The dashboard includes (among other features):</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Main tab with Memory, CPU, Disk</p></li>
<li><p>Thread tab with interactive visualization of thread status and thread usage.
You can select and search for particular thread by name.</p></li>
<li><p>Trace tab, including frequency for each tracepoint. Selection by name and search are available.</p></li>
<li><p>JVM tab for basic JVM information including memory and GC, when a JVM is installed.</p></li>
<li><p>Virtual Appliance tab for information relevant to the particular appliance.
Tabs for Cassandra and Tomcat are currently  available, with more to come.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>To build the dashboard, just includes httpserver in
the module list.  For example:</p>

<p>```</p>

<pre><code>$ make -j 4 image=cassandra,httpserver
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Once the appliance is running, the dashboard is available on port 8000 by default.  (You can change the port using <a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/osv/wiki/cloud-init">cloud-init</a>.)</p>

<p>The <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/osv-dev/tyFGw7NRudA">full 0.14 release announcement</a> is available on the osv-dev mailing list.
You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
