<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cassandra | OSv Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/categories/cassandra/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://osv.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-04T11:43:43-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://osv.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cloudius Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New Dashboard Tab for Insight on Cassandra Virtual Appliances]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/09/18/cassandra-dashboard-tab/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-18T06:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/09/18/cassandra-dashboard-tab</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Tzach Livyatan</strong></p>

<p>We are constantly looking for ways to improve the OSv virtual appliance experience.  The latest improvement is an integrated dashboard, presenting a combination of:</p>

<ul>
<li>OS related metrics (CPU, memory, threads, &hellip;)</li>
<li>Profiling related metrics (trace points)</li>
<li>JVM related metrics (heap, GC, &hellip;)</li>
<li>Cassandra related metrics (latency, tasks, cluster status)</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/cassandra-tab.png" alt="tab" /></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The dashboard is yet another example of using
<a href="osv.io/api/swagger-ui/dist/index.html">REST API</a> to monitor and
control OSv and
OSv virtual appliances. These REST APIs are open for the
user directly. In particular, the new Capstan tab takes advantage of the newly added
<a href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/08/26/jolokia-jmx-connectivity-in-osv/">Jolokia</a>
connector, exposing JMX information over REST.
The OSv REST API makes it simple to manage your OSv virtual appliance with <code>curl(1)</code> or your own script.</p>

<p>There are other great tools out there for JVM monitoring and profiling, like <a href="http://visualvm.java.net/">VisualVM</a>.
The OSv dashboard is unique by unifying the end-to-end virtual appliances functionality:
From the application to the JVM, down to the OS and HW status.</p>

<p>In particular, trace points allow a deep dive into the system execution, providing similar functionality on OSv to what <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DTrace">DTrace</a> does for Solaris.</p>

<p>We are planing to provide similar application-level tabs for other OSv virtual appliances.
Want to build a tab for your favorite application on OSv?
Clone the <a href="https://github.com/cloudius-systems/osv-gui">osv-gui</a> repository and start submitting pull requests!</p>

<p>You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or following <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Speed Run: Running 4 Virtual Appliances on Your Laptop in 5 Seconds Overall]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/09/13/how-fast-can-you-run-4-vm/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-13T23:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/09/13/how-fast-can-you-run-4-vm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>By Dor Laor, Tzach Livyatan</strong></p>

<p>In the following demo, Dor is running 4 different OSv base virtual appliances
on his laptop:</p>

<ul>
<li>Redis</li>
<li>Tomcat</li>
<li>MySQL</li>
<li>Cassandra</li>
</ul>


<p>Each virtual appliance is a full–blown VM, each with a pre-integrated
cloud application, and each launched without terminating the others.</p>

<!-- more -->




<script type="text/javascript" src="https://asciinema.org/a/11914.js" id="asciicast-11914" async></script>


<p>As you can see, application startup time takes between sub-second
(Redis) to a few seconds (Cassandra) depending on the application.
The hypervisor plus OS part of the boot time is less than a second for all cases.</p>

<p>Want more info on Capstan and related topics?  Join the <a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/osv-dev">osv-dev mailing list</a>.  You can get regular OSv updates by subscribing to this blog&rsquo;s feed, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
