<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Events | OSv Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/categories/events/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://osv.io/blog/"/>
  <updated>2015-04-03T15:21:04-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://osv.io/blog/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cloudius Systems]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSv at JavaOne]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/09/25/javaone/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-25T17:10:31-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/09/25/javaone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/speaking-at-javaone.jpg" alt="speaking at JavaOne" /></p>

<p>Glauber Costa and Don Marti are speaking at the JavaOne conference in San Francisco, on Tuesday, September 30.  Hope to see you there.</p>

<p><a href="https://oracleus.activeevents.com/2014/connect/sessionDetail.ww?SESSION_ID=4120">OSv: The Operating System Designed for Java and the Cloud</a></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what you&rsquo;re in for:</p>

<blockquote><p>A lot of the cloud discussion centers around which hypervisors are the best and which management tools will simplify our life the most. But is it the whole story? When problems are addressed from the lower and higher layers, the middleman—the guest operating system—is usually left behind. This changes with OSv, an operating system designed from the ground up to run Java applications in the cloud. OSv is a library OS. Therefore, you can think of using it as being a way to boot a JVM directly into the cloud. Forget OS management: it’s your application and the end of the story. Besides explaining the architecture, this presentation demonstrates how designing an OS with Java in mind can benefit the Java ecosystem.</p></blockquote>

<p>We&rsquo;ll demonstrate a nine-second build of a VM from a Java project.  Hope to see you there.</p>

<p>You can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's the Big Deal About OSv at Cassandra Summit 2014?]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/09/10/cassandra-summit/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-10T16:10:31-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/09/10/cassandra-summit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Pop quiz: what does this graph show?</strong></p>

<p><img src="/images/mystery-graph.png" alt="graph" /></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;d like a hint, here&rsquo;s some context.  It&rsquo;s from the upcoming <a href="http://www.cvent.com/events/cassandra-summit-2014/agenda-176f061a4b144525ae05f18cd9a9cb12.aspx">talk on Cassandra on OSv</a> at Cassandra Summit in San Francisco.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve been picking up a bunch of Cassandra tips at the event so far.  And we&rsquo;re really looking forward to (a) tomorrow&rsquo;s talks from the administrators of large-scale Cassandra sites and (b) showing off a new useful thing that should make life much easier for Cassandra admins who know <code>curl</code>. Which would be&hellip;everyone?</p>

<p>If you missed the chance to see Don Marti and Glauber Costa at Linuxcon/CloudOpen, please come see us, with bonus extra speaker <strong>Dor Laor</strong>.  Otherwise, you can keep up with the latest OSv news from this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>

<p>(Next up: <a href="http://www.xenproject.org/about/events/viewevent/120-xen-project-user-summit-2014.html">Xen Project User Summit</a> in New York City&hellip;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSv in the Spotlight at LinuxCon/CloudOpen 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/08/20/linuxcon-cloudopen/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-20T16:10:31-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/08/20/linuxcon-cloudopen</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>While we relax and don&rsquo;t have to fix anything on our slides (really, they&rsquo;re all done), other speakers at the Linux Foundation&rsquo;s <a href="http://events.linuxfoundation.org/events/cloudopen-north-america">CloudOpen North America conference</a> in beautiful Chicago have some observations to make about OSv.</p>

<p><img src="/images/chicago-river.jpeg" alt="Chicago River" /></p>

<p><strong>The Linux Foundation always picks great conference locations.</strong></p>

<p><a href="http://lccona14.sched.org/speaker/rcpavlicek">Russell Pavlicek</a> from the Xen project mentioned several library OSs that run on Xen in his <a href="http://lccona14.sched.org/event/17fdf31e5913cc4ebd5cf1f2ec039aa0">talk on new Xen features</a>.  He called the concept &ldquo;one of the biggest advances in the cloud.&rdquo;  Earlier library OSs have shown how much performance and simplicity gains are available, and OSv is extending the idea to ordinary POSIX and Java applications.</p>

<p><a href="http://lccona14.sched.org/speaker/mikeday">Mike Day</a> from IBM said, &ldquo;the engineers who write OSv are really good C++ coders,&rdquo; and called the project &ldquo;some of the finest C++ source code I&rsquo;ve ever seen&rdquo; in his <a href="http://lccona14.sched.org/event/434032efc316cc7aa98d4d590abda72e">talk on cloud operating systems for servers</a>.  He also had some praise for the <a href="http://osv.io/blog/blog/2014/04/19/spinlock-free/">spinlock-free way</a> that OSv handles mutexes, which as regular readers of this blog will know is important to prevent the dreaded lock-holder preemption problem.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re at LinuxCon, excuse me, #linuxcon, please come over and say &ldquo;hi&rdquo; to the OSv speakers: Don Marti and Glauber Costa. Hope to see you at the event, and please come to &ldquo;<a href="http://lccona14.sched.org/event/4684a80dd37f200277e971133920a2d0">Beating the Virtualization Tax for NoSQL Workloads With OSv</a>&rdquo; on Friday at 10:45 in the Colorado room.   Otherwise, you can get general OSv updates by subscribing to this blog&rsquo;s <a href="http://osv.io/blog/atom.xml">feed</a>, or folllowing <a href="https://twitter.com/CloudiusSystems">@CloudiusSystems</a> on Twitter.</p>

<p><strong>Chicago River photo: <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Chicago_river_2004.jpg">Urban for Wikimedia Commons</a></strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
